<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A playne declaration made at Oxforde the 24. daye of July, by mayster Richarde Smyth, Doctor of diuinite, vpon hys Retractation made [and] published at Paules crosse in London, in the yeare of our lorde God, D.D.xlvii. the xv. daye of May</title>
            <author>Smith, Richard, 1500-1563.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1547</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12496</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22824</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104734</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840467</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840467</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4976</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12496)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4976)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 146:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A playne declaration made at Oxforde the 24. daye of July, by mayster Richarde Smyth, Doctor of diuinite, vpon hys Retractation made [and] published at Paules crosse in London, in the yeare of our lorde God, D.D.xlvii. the xv. daye of May</title>
                  <author>Smith, Richard, 1500-1563.</author>
                  <author>Smith, Richard, 1500-1563. Godly and faythfull retractation. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By Reynolde Wolfe],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Domini M.D.XLVII. [1547]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes text of Smith's "A godly and faythfull retractation" (STC 22822).</note>
                  <note>At foot of title page: Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from colophon.</note>
                  <note>With a final colophon leaf.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴ E⁶.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4976:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4976:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>A PLAYNE</hi> Declaration made at Oxforde the 24. daye of Iuly, by Mayſter Richarde Smyth, Doctor of diuinite, vpon hys Retracta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion made &amp; publiſhed at Paules croſſe in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, In the yeare of oure Lorde God, M. D. xlvij. the xv. daye of May.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Londini, Anno Domini M. D. XLVII.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio ad impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum ſolum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4976:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:4976:2"/>
            <head>A playne Declaration made at Oxforde the 24. daye of Iuly by Mayſter Richard Smyth Doctor of diuini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye, vpon hys Retractation made &amp; publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed at Paules croſſe in London, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> xv. daye of Maye Anno Domini M. D. xlvij.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Alomon ſaieth <hi>Dominus prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get gradie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ſim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pliciter:</hi> God wil defende them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> walke playnely At my fyrſt re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>torne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don immediatly after my Sermon whiche I made laſt at Pawles Croſſe accordynge to my bounden deuty &amp; promys, I ſholde haue chiefely &amp; moſte princypally declared and ſet furth plainely and fully here in Oxforde all that my Retractation wyche I red and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed openly at Paules croſſe. But in this behalf I vtterly deceaued
<pb facs="tcp:4976:3"/> my ſelfe: For I did omytt and let paſſe my moſte weighte matter, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I intendid to ſet furth thre thinges at once. The one was too ſhewe that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Declaration of al my doynges as towchyng my bokes, was but a Retractation and not a Recantation. The ſecond was the earneſt anſwering vnto ſuche (as I harde ſaye) had conceauid by myſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kynge of my Retractation, that I ſhulde denie and condempne the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of thalter (wherein ys pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very body &amp; blode of Chriſt) and the ſacrament of Baptiſme. The laboringe in theis two thingꝭ withdrewe and troubled me verye muche that I coulde not earneſtly trauayle in ſettynge forth of my re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tractation accordyng to my dutye. For as touchyng the firſt where as I ſayde I made a retractation and not a recantacion, it was but an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe
<pb facs="tcp:4976:3"/> of my doynges. For as moche is commenly ſignified and ment by Retractation as by recantacion. And becauſe that all men for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt parte whiche herde me ſo ſay do ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther and take hereof (as I am credi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bly infourmed) that I dyd ſticke ſtyll and ſtand to mine old doctrine in all thinges: And that the retrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion ſent abrode in my name was either none of myne, or elles that I was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled and forced to agre vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to it: I am verye ſorye that they ſo dyd miſtake me. But I am moſte ſorye of all that I for my parte tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough my darke vtteraunce ſhulde geue them occaſion ſo to thinke. Wherfore at this tyme I purpoſe to rede vnto you my retraction whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che I declared at Paulis croſſe, vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the whiche I agreed and conſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted frely and wyllyngly without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny maner of force or compulſion.
<pb facs="tcp:4976:4"/> And to thentent you ſhall well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue that this is my doctrine and my belefe, I ſhal to my power both now and at al tymes hereafter, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> occaſion ſhal ſerue, ſet forth, mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne and defende the ſame. And here I ſhall mooſt erneſtly requyre you, and in our ſauiour Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche you, nother to miſtake me on the one ſyde, nother to be offended or greued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me on the other ſyde. For in this my retractation I do not deny the holy ſacrament of the aulter, nor the Sacrament of bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſme, nor finally any other thinge compriſed in the body of holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture as neceſſarie matter of our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief. And where as ſyns the tyme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I declared my retractatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Paw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis croſſe I wrote and ſente abrode ſondry letters for myne excuſe, and made alſo as it were a gloſe and an expoſition of my ſayd retractacion, whereby I myghte ſeme rather to
<pb facs="tcp:4976:4"/> trauayle for to preſerue myne eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, then clerely and ſyncerely to ſet furth the doctrine whiche I in my retractation wyllynglye dyd profeſſe: In this and in al other my writinges, readynges and teachin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, what ſo euer I haue written, read or taught heretofore, this that I now teache I knowe to be true. For that I haue groundely tried &amp; ſerched the ſame. We haue a ſaieng <hi>Amicus Socrates amicus Plato, magis amica VERITAS:</hi> He is my frende, and he is my frend, but the truth is moſte my frende. Truthe is to be in braced, truth is to be defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, truth is my profeſſion. Nother my fame nor eſtimation of my ſelfe, nother frendſhyp of my dere frendes, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other thinges ſhall make me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of truth. I remembre what the Lord of truth doth ſay: He that is aſhamed of me before men, I ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:4976:5"/> be aſhamed of hym before my father which is in heauen. Nowe therfore I wyll reade vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to you my Retractation.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He holy Prophet Dauid (good chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten audie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce) ſaith right truly: <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis homo mendax.</hi> That is to wytt: Euery man is a Lyer of his owne corrupted nature: The which thing how trew it is, theldeſt &amp; beſt Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the Chriſten Church, doo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidently declare, becauſe they all haue erred in their bookes Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the great Clerke ſaynt Auſten, in an Epiſtle writen to Marcella writeth of himſelf: <hi>Vos qui me mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4976:5"/> 
                  <hi>diligitis, ſi talem me aſſeritis, vtnun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam in ſcriptis erraſſe me dic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tis, fruſtra laboratis, nec bonam cauſam ſuſcepiſtis; facile meipſo iudice ſuperamini, quonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non placet mihi cum a chariſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>is meis ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lis exiſtimor, qualis non ſum.</hi> That is to ſay: Yee that loue me muche, if ye ſaid that I am ſuch that ye affirme that I neuer erred in my writyngs or Bokes, ye labor in vayne, ye ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue not taken in hand a good cauſe: ye are eaſely ouercome, I my ſelfe being Iudge: For it pleaſeth not me whan I am eſtemed ſuche a man of my moaſt deare frendes as I am not. Here we ſe that this bleſſed father ſaynt Auſten was not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to confeſſe his error in writing: which thing he dyd not by woordes only, but alſo in a certayne Booke wherin he wrote very many things in which he confeſſeth that he was deceyued. This Booke is called in
<pb facs="tcp:4976:6"/> Latyn, <hi>Liber Retractationum:</hi> And in Englyſh, a Booke of Retracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or Reuocations, of ſuch thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges whiche he wrote amyſſe &amp; erred in. Shall I now be aſhamed to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knoledge my ſelf to haue ben decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in my Booke of Traditions? Am I worthy to be reſembled or compared to this noble aunciente Doctor of Chriſtes church? Wyl ye not beleue S. Auſten in other poyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of our Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> becauſe he erred, &amp; alſo confeſſed his error in dyuerſe and ſundry thynges of his bokes? To be ſhort, who of all the Writers of bokes erred not? S, Ambros, S, Hierome, Chriſoſtome, Hilary, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian, Origen, Tertulian, and all the other Doctors of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church were deceyued in ſome poyntes of their Bookes, as learned men do well know. Why therfore may nott. I erre, or why ſhulde I be aſhamed
<pb facs="tcp:4976:6"/> too confeſſe myne Error and too re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke it? Ought not euery good ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and woman too be eſory for my fall in this my Booke, and too reioyce with me acknowledging the trewth in this matier of mans Traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Preceptes, Ordinaunces, Rites, Ce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>remonies? Who ſeeth not that I haue a iuſt cauſe to excuſe my weke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and fault and aſke of you mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy? which I truſt I haue outayned of the Kynges gracious highneſſe, and his mooſt honorable Counſell: by whoſe goodneſſe and elemency I am here admytted and ſuffered too ſhew myne Errors and Faultes in my booke of Traditions, which I made of late entituled thus: A brief Treatiſe, ſetting furth diuerſe tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, neceſſary both too be beleued of Chriſten people and kepte alſo, which ar not expreſſed in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, but lefte to the Churche by the
<pb facs="tcp:4976:7"/> Apoſtles Traditions, made and ſet furth by Richard Smyth, Doctor of Diuinite and Reder of it in Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde. Which Booke I do Reproue &amp; Reuoke in dyuers Faultes in it, of the which I wyll a non recite cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne perticulerly, and then I ſhall geue vnto you a trew and Generall Doctrine of all thoſe thynges of which I doo entrete in that my Boke, that therby you may well perceyue &amp; ſee, after what ſorte thei ought too be taken of Chriſten people that no man erre therin *</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4976:7"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>FYRST,</hi> Wheras I ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kyng in my booke of Traditions, of the autorite of Byſſhoppes in makyng lawes and ordenances, whyche the people ought to obey, I dyd ſay &amp; teache in this wyſe: That men ought to obey the Byſſhoppes com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundement in all thynges leaful, vpon payne of euerlaſtyng damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon. And that theſe wordes of Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thew: Doo as they byd you, but not as they doo, be vnderſtand not only of thinges conteined in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, but alſo of the Churches or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces beſydes Scripture made by the Miniſters of the Churche, although the ſaid Miniſters do ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe their auctorite for their owne be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nefite and profite. And further, where I taught that it is more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient that the people obey their Biſſhops co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes &amp; De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees although it be but in a thinge
<pb facs="tcp:4976:8"/> indifferent of it ſelfe and not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded by God, then that ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſhuld obey their maiſters, or chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren their fathers and mothers. And finally, where I ſayd concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng the ſame matter: That as ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iectes be bounde to obey and fulfyll their Princes Lawes, which ar not conteyned in Gods Lawes beyng not agaynſt it, euen ſo be Chriſten people bounde too obey &amp; doo that which their Biſſhops byddeth them doo. All theſe ſayinges I doo now Reuoke, Diſanull and Condempne as erronious and falſe. And do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe and acknowledge fyrſt that the auctorite aſwell of the Byſſhop of Rome, whoſe auctorite is iuſtly and lawfully abolyſhed in this Realme as of other Biſſhops &amp; other called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſters of the church, conſiſteth in the diſpenſacion and miniſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Gods woorde, &amp; not in makyng
<pb facs="tcp:4976:8"/> Lawes, Ordinaunces and Decrees ouer the people beſyde Gods word without the conſent and auctoritie of the Prince and people.</p>
               <p>¶ Secondly, I ſay &amp; affirme that no Byſſhop nor none of the Clergy aſſembled togither haue auctoritie to make any Lawes or Decrees beſydes Gods Law ouer the people without the conſent of the Princes and the people: and if they do make anye ſuche, no man is bounde to obey theym.</p>
               <p>¶ Thirdly, I ſay that in thoſe cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tryes, where by the auctorite of the Prince they haue made any ſuche Lawes, thauctorite of thoſe Lawes doth not appende and hang of the Biſſhops and the Clergy, but of the princes &amp; cheif heds in euery cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try</p>
               <p>¶ Fourthly, I ſay &amp; affirme that within this Realme of England &amp; other the kinges Dominions, there
<pb facs="tcp:4976:9"/> is no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Conſtitution <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and auaileable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but only by the kynges ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyes au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ority or of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>And where in my foreſaid booke of Traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, I ſayd that Tenthes of Benefices be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> only to theym that do preche and teche the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and alſo that he that ſerueth not the Aulter nor precheth not the Goſpell can nott iuſtly lyue by the Tenthes, but is in conſcience bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to reſtore the profites and frutes taken therby: Which my ſayenges as it lieth in woordes &amp; ſentences is ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>itious and ſclaunderous to the Kynges maieſties procedinges and the Lawes and Ordres of this Realme, which haue graunted Ten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thes and Tythes to many Ley per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones: Therfore this my ſayeng as it may be taken, &amp; iuſtly by the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:4976:9"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> they be put, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to defende nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>: but I requyre that I may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> theym and declare theim gently, that I ment not in theſe my ſayinges of any. Lay men, to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation of the Lawes and Statu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of this Realme: but I ment only of Curates and Preeſtes which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuing their Tythes, do not their dutyes accordingly,</p>
               <p>And where alſo in my ſayd booke of Traditions, and lykewyſe in my boke of the Sacrifice of the Maſſe, I followyng Pamaſcene and other Auncient Authors, wrote, that the Diſciples of Chriſt dyd make cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne Canons, which ſaint Clement dyd gether togither and put in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng, and that theſe ſame Canons muſt be taken for the Appoſtles do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and techyng, and their woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des without doubt to be beleued &amp; kepte as that which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyned ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely
<pb facs="tcp:4976:10"/> in ſcripture. Now hauynge red many thynges, whiche at that tyme I had not diligently marked &amp; wayed: I doo thinke, affirme, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe that doctrine to be not trew, but a vayne, vnlawfull, vniuſt, and vnportable burdein to Chriſten con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſciences: And that thoſe Canons pretended to be of thappoſtles ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and gatherd of ſaint Clement, not to be made of thappoſtles: or if they were, not to be made otherwiſe than but for an order in the Church for that tyme, not euer for to endure wherof many at this tyme in no wyſe be too be obſerued: And thoſe which do remayne, not to be of that force as Gods lawe to charge mens conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces otherwiſe, then as mans Ordinaunces and Policie whiche may be taken away by Superior powers aſwel &amp; with ſo lytle ſcruple of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience as other of them which
<pb facs="tcp:4976:10"/> many yeres a go were taken away, &amp; to ſum clene contrary lawes made</p>
               <p>In the ſaid boke of Traditions alſo I ſayd &amp; affirmed, that Chriſt and his Appoſtles taught and lefte to the church many thingꝭ without writyng which we muſt both beleue ſtedfaſtly &amp; alſo fulfyll obediently vnder payne of dampnation euer to endure. Amongeſt the which I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſed by name a greate nomber to be obeyed, kepte &amp; folowed: as the obſeruation of Lent from fleſh or wyne, the kepyng of the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the Pyx, the receyuing of it at the preeſtes handes, the hallowyng of the water in the Font, the thriſe dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng of the Chylde in the water at the Chriſtenyng, the puttyng, on of the Chriſome, the Conſecration of the Oyle, &amp; Anoyntyng of the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened chylde, the hallowyng of the Aulters, the prayeng towardes the
<pb facs="tcp:4976:11"/> Taſt, the Senſyng of the aultare, the Waſſhyng of the handes, &amp; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng Confiteor, and li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ting vp of the Sacrament at the Maſſe, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng or Holy Water, That the .xii Appoſtles (euery man a peece for his portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) made the Crede, &amp; many mo beſydes theſe. And after lyke ſorte I ſpake of Canons, Decrees, and Ordinaunces of byſſhops and generall counſels.</p>
               <p>Now I do confeſſe the ſaide do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine as concernyng thobſeruyng of the ſayd Traditions vnder that payne, to be falſe and Tirannicall, an vniuſt, vnlawfull, and vntrew burdein of mens conſciences, not fit to be taught, preched, or defended,</p>
               <p>Lykewyſe of the beleuynge of thinges where I dyd ſay, that there are dyuerſe thynges not expreſſed in the ſcripture which we are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to beleue egally with thoſe thynges
<pb facs="tcp:4976:11"/> which arr written in Scripture, in the nomber o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which I dyd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſely &amp; indiſcretely for an example bring ſome of the afore reherſed and other many. As co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyng many things in my booke put, and the more nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber there by me reconed and named, I affirme and ſay to be falſe, and in no wyſe trew, but very daungerous and vniuſt, onerous to the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of chriſten men: and too be trew only in thoſe Doctrines which neceſſaryly may be gathered, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently doo folow too the wordes and ſentences in Scripture, ſo that in effect they may be iuſtly counted to be in ſcripture, though the very fourme of woordes be not there: Of the which in my Booke is very few, yet ſome I dyd reherſe: as <hi>Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus pueroru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Deſcenſus Chriſti ad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeros, Virginitas Marie, Trinitas perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narum, Proceſſio Spiritus ſancti,</hi> and a
<pb facs="tcp:4976:12"/> few other.</p>
               <p>And bicauſe I wold declare the trew acception, dignitie and aucto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie of ſcripture too be diſtincte, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe, &amp; of higher, ſurer, more ſtable and firme order and credence, then the other vnwritten Tradicions &amp; Aſſertions, wandring in thobſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of many yeres, &amp; the churches canons and Decrees, ordinaunces and traditions left by ſucceſſion.</p>
               <p>Here I do declare, ſet furth, con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe, affirme, and aſſerte my trew &amp; ſtedfaſt opinion, belefe and fayth in theſe thynges propounded &amp; vttred vnto me as concernyng ſcripture written, and other Traditions vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written and not declared in the ſaid holy Scripture. <note place="margin">1 Thaucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ite of ſcri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ture.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The ſcripture of tholde and new Teſtament written by thinſpiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Holy ghoſt concernyng our belefe, is too be beleued, accepted &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:4976:12"/> taken as an vndoubted truthe, not to be altered, refourmed or chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by any man, nor to be miniſhed nor abrogate by any cuſtome, but vnder perell of dampnation to be beleued, and vnder the ſame daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to be followed, hauyng aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto it by almightie god, taught &amp; enſpired by the holy ghoſt dependyng of no mans auctoritie, nor violable or defeſible by any po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, otherwiſe then vnder the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell &amp; dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of eternall damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>Suche thynges as in the Actes <note place="margin">2 Thinges i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ptur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for a tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> commau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded.</note> of the Apoſtles or any other place of Scripture, as for a tyme was taught and ſetfurthe for an intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of the weake in the fayth, not to remayne for euer, as fayth increſed was abrogate, none other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than it was thauctors mynde and intente they ſhuld: thoſe that concerned eatyng, drinkyng, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng
<pb facs="tcp:4976:13"/> or diſcoueryng of heades, or ſuch other externe rites and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyes, rather concernyng an ordre among men outwardly to be for a tyme obſerued, than an eternall law to rule and gouerne the ſoule.</p>
               <p>Suche thynges as ſometyme be <note place="margin">3 Thinges <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eceſſary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of ſcri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ture.</note> called traditions not expreſſely and by wordes found in holy ſcripture, but which may neceſſarily and well be gathered of holy ſcripture, are to be beleued and followed, in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche &amp; as farr as they may truly be gathered of the ſcripture, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently doo follow the wourdes and intentes of the ſame.</p>
               <p>Traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s pretended to be made <note place="margin">4 Thynges <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> beleife <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arily ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hered of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cripture.</note> of thappoſtles, &amp; by ſome authors aſcribed to theym as concernyng thinges to be beleued not found in ſcripture directly nor neceſſarily, &amp; directly conſecutyng &amp; followyng to ſcripture, laufully &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out perell of
<pb facs="tcp:4976:13"/> dampnation may be doubted of, &amp; alſo denyed and refuſed by the ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior powers; &amp; ſuche as haue Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoritie in the church.</p>
               <p>There be many thinges aſcribed <note place="margin">5 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ed f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ed dic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ous. doc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> to thappoſtles, &amp; called traditions deduced from the tyme of thappo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles &amp; read in the name of olde Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, and ſet furth vnder the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſed title of their name, which be feyned, forged &amp; nothing trew, full of ſuperſtition and vntrewth, fey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by theym which wold magnify their owne power and auctoritie, as is the Epiſtles of Clemens, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cletus, Euariſtus and Fabianus, &amp; other which arr ſet furth by the byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome and his complices, which be forged, feyned and of none auctoritie nor to be beleued, but cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terfeyted by theym: who with the color of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tiquitie, wolde magnify that v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ped power of the byſſhop of Rome.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4976:14"/>
               <p> Traditions of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">Thinges <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ncerni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>aners <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>rely ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hered or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cripture.</note> they be in deed or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the begyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; the tyme of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> haue ben appoynted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of later dayes by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> by generall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perioritie of one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                     <desc>•••…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Watching, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Senſynges, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and all other ſuche Rites, Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyes and comen Orders to be vſed in the church of God, doth not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ynd but where they be receyued, and by diſuſe maye be abrogate, or by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary law made in any countrey by thauctority of the ſuperior powers may be clene taken away, &amp; other Rites, Canons, Traditions &amp; Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonyes brought in for them with out any dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of ſynne or grudge
<pb facs="tcp:4976:14"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. And with any ſuche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the kynges <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> may either <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> cauſe, or of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> any cauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> man fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> with whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> haue diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> free from them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vſe his ſaid lybertie with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſynne or ſcruple of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, either to the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges maieſtie which gaue lybertie, or to him whiche hath obteyned the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>penſacion. None o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe than in any other acte, ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute or proclamation made by hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane polycie, the kynges maieſtye and the hygh powers may. Whan contrary wyſe that that is Goddes law and commaunded by ſcripture alwaies to be obſerued, no man can
<pb facs="tcp:4976:15"/> diſpence with if, nor gyue any man libertie to breake it, vnder daunger of ſynne &amp; corruption of conſcience.</p>
               <p>This is my full, firme, and ſtable bele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e as touchynge the ſcripture written, &amp; Traditions vnwritten, &amp; what thyng ſoeuer I or any other heretofore haue preached, taught, written or endyted to the contrary of theſe my aſſertions &amp; belefe now declared vnto you: or if any man hereafter (which God forbyd) ſhuld preach, teach or ſet furth any thing which is not conſonaunt &amp; agreyng to theſe aforeſayd articles and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſercions, beleue good hearers, and know you iurely, that it is a falſe, vntrew &amp; deuellyſh doctrine and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>godlye vſurpation vpon the holly Scripture, contrary too the trew, pure, and Catholicall doctrine of Chriſtes churche. In the which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aythe and beleef conteyned in the
<pb facs="tcp:4976:15"/> ſayd. vi. Aſſertions, I doo entende good hearers with the grace of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God to lyue by Chriſt, and all my hope is alſo too dye therin if need ſhalbe. And whenſoeuer God ſhall call me therunto (his grace aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtyng) I ſhalbe redy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> now concernyng another booke whiche I made of the Sacrifice of the Maſſe, where the moaſt chief and principall article of our fayth, and moaſt directly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teynyng too the redemption of our ſynnes and to our ſaluation is: That our ſauyor Chriſt Ieſu by his moaſt precious death and effuſion of his moaſt precious blood vpon the croſſe dyd redeme man kynde, taking away our ſynnes, pacifying the indignation of his father, and cancellyng thobligation that was agaynſt vs: In which Sacrifice
<pb facs="tcp:4976:16"/> makyng vnto his father, our ſayde Sauyoure Iheſus Chriſt as ſaynt Paule ſayth playnly to the Hebrew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es, was not a preeſt after the order of Aaron, foraſmuch as he was of another Trybe: and alſo, that preeſthod was impertite and vnpro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fitable bringyng nothyng too per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: But our Sauyour Chriſt made his ſacrifice vpon the Croſſe parfectly, abſolutely, and with the moſt hygheſt perfection that could be, ſomuch, that after that one ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and ſacrifice for ſyn made by hym but once only, nother he nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other creature ſhuld at any tyme after, make any mo oblacions for the ſame. And for as that ſaynt Paule ſayth, he was called an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall preeſt of the order of Melchy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedech, and not of Aaron.</p>
               <p>This fayth ought euery man and woman vndoubtedly to beleue and
<pb facs="tcp:4976:16"/> openly to profeſſe vpon payne of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtyng dampnation, and alſo too dye in this profeſſyon if caſe ſhall ſo requyre: The which moaſt holſome &amp; moaſt neceſſary doctrine of our fayth I not dilygently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideryng, as many tymes too right great clerkes &amp; lerned men in much writynge in lyke mattiers it hath chaunced to ſay too far. The infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite and weakeneſſe of men beyng ſuche, that ſeldome in many words error hath eſcaped. So in my boke of the Sacrifice of the maſſe, I dyd incircumſpectly &amp; raſhly write and ſet furth too the people, that Chriſt was not a preeſt after the order of Melchiſedech, whan he offred him ſelfe vpon the Croſſe too his father for our ſynnes, but was a preeſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the order of Aaron. And that when Chriſt dyd offer his owne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy too his father after thorder of
<pb facs="tcp:4976:17"/> Melchiſedech <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, it may not be vnderſtand of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the croſſe, but of the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice that Chriſt made at his Maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in forme of bread and wyne. To the which in dede ſaynt Paules do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is contrary, both in other pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, and in thepiſtle ad Hebreos ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry manifeſtlye, agaynſt whom (who without doubt had the very ſpirite of God) Neither it becommeth, nor I wyl not willingly teach or defend any thinge. Wherfore you ſhall im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pute that, good Audience, too the frailtye of mans nature, and too my negligent marking, hauing at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> tyme rather a reſpecte too a fantaſy that then I had in my mynde, than too the trew and infallible doctrine of ſcripture. And moreouer in the ſame my booke, I ſayd not only that the Sacrifice of the maſſe is the ſelfe ſame ſubſtaunce of chriſte,
<pb facs="tcp:4976:17"/> but alſo the ſelfe ſame oblacion or offeryng of our ſauyoure Chriſtes very fleſh and blood which him ſelf once offrid to his father on the croſſe to appeaſe his wrath. And that the preeſtes do continually and daily in the maſſe offre not onely the ſelfe ſame body of Chriſt, but alſo to the ſame effecte, that Chriſt dyd offre himſelfe to his father at his Maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy. Of the which wordes and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, if they be not very warely &amp; circumſpectly reade, and more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorably taken then the wordes as they lye, may well bere, it might be gatherd, that preeſtes herein be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall with Chriſt. Preeſtes of thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Melchiſedech, appeaſing the wrath &amp; indignation of the father of heauen, crucifying or offeryng Chriſt to the ſame effecte that Chriſt in his owne perſone dyd vpon the croſſe, which is a blaſphemy into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable
<pb facs="tcp:4976:18"/> to be herd of chriſten eares. For Chriſt as ſaynt Paule ſayth, was but once offered, once gaue vp himſelfe for the redemption of our ſynnes on good friday on the croſſe, nor neuer before nor after was offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for vs, but in a ſacrament and as a commemoration of the ſame. And ſo of the Maundy or Supper of our Lorde, Chriſt himſelf ſayth <hi>Hec quotieſcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> feceritis, in meam com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorationem ſacietis.</hi> Ones he dyed for our ſynnes, and once agayne he roſe for our iuſtification. He dyeth no more, &amp; his ſacrifice was ſo good ſo ful, ſo pleaſant, ſo precious to god, that there needed no more oblatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to appeaſe god, nor only for the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes paſt, but alſo for all the ſynnes to the day of Doome.</p>
               <p>There neede no more ſacrifices, no more offerers, but as hauyng a reſpect and a remembraunce of that
<pb facs="tcp:4976:18"/> moſt holy, moſt perfyte, and moſt entier Lambe, then &amp; for euer offred vp for vs. But theſe before ſayd I can not deny but ſpoken of me and written, And as I do not now lyke theym, ſo at thexample of ſaint Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten and other good doctors, I am not aſhamed to retracte theym, call theim agayne, &amp; condempne theim. For when I folowed myne own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention not directed by Scripture, I began as the nature of man is to wander, and at the laſt went cleane contrary too Gods woord.</p>
               <p>Wherfore, I hertely exhort euery man as touchyng matiers of faith to founde the ſame vpon Gods cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyn, trew, and infallyble woorde: leſt by doyng the contrary, they fall into ſuperſtition, idolatry, &amp; other manyfold errers as I my ſelf ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme, and many other (although I doo not come hyther too accuſe any
<pb facs="tcp:4976:19"/> man) yet I perceyue of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> tyme haue doone. Wherfore, theſe my two bookes, the one of the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the maſſe, and thother of the Traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vnwritten, in thoſe poyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes before reherſed, &amp; all other wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in they be not full co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſonent to ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I forſake &amp; renounce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> erroneous, and agaynſt the trew woord of God. Requiring the good chriſten reder whoſoeuer ſhall rede theym, to geue no further <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vnto theym then I wold my falſe: That is, not to take as vndoubted truth all that is therin written; but as written of a man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> falleth: to be ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> be conſonaunt to ſcripture, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they be not agaynſt ſcripture, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> humane perſuaſion, which may ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſone ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> conſonaunt to ſcripture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4976:19"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> that I muche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> that I wrote them in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe pointes, And I deſyre euery man that hath any of the ſayd bokes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of theym, and to gyue no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>m in all ſuch thinges in them written, as be not conſonant to the ſcripture, as they auoyde occa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and tendre the truthe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and his glory <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> vnderſtand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of my doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4+ letters">
                     <desc>••••…</desc>
                  </gap> which I preached here in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eportinge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe .iiii. thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>: y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rites of chriſt: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> perſone and the
<pb facs="tcp:4976:20"/> worthines of the worke The truth is they dyd miſtake me, applieng thoſe wordes to our iuſtification, whiche I ſpake of the workes of a man that is alredy iuſtified. But to thintente that no man hereafter ſhal wauer or doute of my faith and conſcience, in the matter of iuſtification: This is my certaine &amp; true doctrine therein, wherein I am fully reſolued and per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuaded, whiche I haue euer taughte ſyns I haue ben a teacher of the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pture, purpoſing (god willing) euer to remaine in the ſame. This I ſaye and affirme good audience, that this ſaienge; that we be iuſtified by onely fayth in Chriſt, is no newe inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſaieng or propoſition, but many tymes vſed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt and moſte aunci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent doctours: as Origen, ſaint Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyl, ſaint Chryſoſtome, Ambroſe, S. Barnarde, and diuers other m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>and is a ſure and vndoubtfull truthe ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="tcp:4976:20"/> of them in this meaninge and ſence, to ſeclude and put awaye the merites of al mens dedes, how good ſo euer they ſemed to be, and onelye to aſcribe the glorye and merite of our iuſtification to Chriſt and to his holy bloud and paſſion, by which we are ſanctified, redemed &amp; made good So that it was of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſed to abate our pryde, and to take away our glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhuld truely acknowledge in vs the benefite of god, the weaknes, imbecillitie, and inſufficiencie of our ſelues, not that a Chriſtian ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may contemne or diſpiſe good workes, or that we ſhulde thinke a chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s lyfe to be an ydle &amp; a ſluggiſhe lyfe, deſtitute of the feare of god, hope, re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pentaunce, charitie, prayer, faſtyng, almes dedes, and all good workes, and obedience to the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of god. But that we ſhulde acknowledge, that when we haue
<pb facs="tcp:4976:21"/> done al that euer we can do, that we are but vnprofitable ſeruauntes, &amp; haue deſerued no thankes for oure workes or merites, but by the mere grace and goodnes of god through the merites only of his dereſte belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſonne Chriſt Ieſus. Which doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trine that onely fayth in Chriſt doth thus iuſtifie, is true, catholyke, and a neceſſarye doctrine to be taught to chriſten men in this maner: The whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che doctrine the moſte parte of all which I haue redde of the auncient doctors do confeſſe and teache. And therfore it may after this ſort iuſtly and truly be ſet forth publyſhed and taught alſo among vs chriſten men, although this ſayeng hath ben euyl taken and depraued of ſome as falſe and erronious. And if a man in dede ſhulde thynke thus, that beleuinge well (yf a man myght do ſo) and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge euyll or doinge nothinge at all accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinge
<pb facs="tcp:4976:21"/> to his belefe and profeſſion hauynge tyme and ſpace therto, yet he ſhold be ſaued, he ſurely thinketh folyſhly and madly and ſo as neuer lerned man wrote or thoughte that was a chriſten man and in his right wyttes. For ſcripture is playne: He that loueth God kepeth his comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes: And they that be Chriſtes ſhepe, heare his voice: and do theraf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter. wherfore they that take prechers teachinge that we be iuſtified by on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye faith as though they wold haue them do no good workes, they take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wrongfully, folyſhly, &amp; contrary to their true meaninge, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande them not: whoſe meaninge is (as I ſuppoſe) to ſhew the wekenes of man, and the goodnes of god: the infirmite of vs, the benefyt of chriſt: the imperfectnes of our workes, tha boundaunt grace of our ſauiour: tha batynge of our pride, the glory of the
<pb facs="tcp:4976:22"/> croſſe of Chriſt: mans weakenes and gods power. And in veray deede all our workes faſtynge, praiers, almes deades, paines, tormentes, pouertie, abſtinence, and all kynde of ſuffring, which a man is able to do or abyde, is not able to deſerue or to get remiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion of ſinne, For it is only the mere mercy and great liberalite of almigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye god, thorowe onely deathe of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, that frely pardo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth our offences, and maketh vs ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceptable to him. In whom we bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge faythfully, and puttynge al oure confidence and truſte in him, and fully and firme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cleauynge to him, can not be deceaued, but on his backe and with him we ſhalbe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried into the houſe of his father in heauen</p>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:4976:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
